ANS Record Group 2: Curatorial, 1858-ongoing
American Numismatic Society
ANS Record Group 2: Curatorial
1858-ongoing
Includes records relating to coins accessioned and held by the ANS, such as accession register log books, correspondence, wills, estate documents, unrestricted gift forms, card indexes, coin envelopes and related materials, as well as correspondence and other records produced and kept by ANS curators.
64.75 cubic feet
American Numismatic Society
PORTIONS OF THE FINDING AID ARE SUPPRESSED FROM PUBLIC VIEW. ANS staff can log into Staff View for the full record group description.
Organized into the following series: (1) Coin collection accession register log books, 1858-ongoing; (2) Coin collection card index, 1859-1904, bulk 1892-1901; (3) Coin collection accession records by accession number 1894, 1920-2004; (4) Coin collection accession records by subject and year, 1911-2007; (5) Coin collection deaccession records, 1958-2009; (6) Curatorial loan records, 1918-2007, bulk 1980-2007; (7) Exhibition records, 1900-2010; (8) Envelopes from Bates and Heaton coin collections, 1984-1985; (9) Howland Wood curator correspondence and other material; 1913-1937; (10) George C. Miles curator correspondence, research materials, and lectures, 1933-1974; (11) Henry Grunthal curator correspondence, 1967-1969; (12) Michael L. Bates curator correspondence and coin photographs, 1958-2004; (13) Jeremiah D. Brady curator correspondence, 1916-1981, bulk 1976-1979; (14) Nancy M. Waggoner curator correspondence and other material, 1968-1989; (15) Alan M. Stahl curator correspondence and other material, 1914-2000, bulk 1982-2000; (15) Carmen Arnold-Biucchi curator correspondence, 1982-1999; (16) Rose Chan Houston curator correspondence, 1947-1988; (17) William L. Bischoff curator correspondence, 1987; (18) William E. Metcalf curator correspondence, 1954-2000, bulk 1982-2000; (19) Miscellaneous collection records.
Parts of this finding aid, including descriptive notes and container lists, can only be viewed by logging in to Staff View.
Access
Portions are closed to outside researchers.
  nnan0115
- Series 1: Coin collection accession register log books, 1858-ongoing; 3 cubic feet (7 bound items)
  Portions are closed to outside researchers.
  Accession registers; Logs (Records)
  Consists of seven coin collection accession register log books, in which are listed accession number, date, a brief description, country, denomination, material, donor or seller, and cost. The level of descriptive detail among the entries varies. These books have been the official record of accessions since the Society’s founding in 1858.
    nnan0115/c_0aab36a084829eb75b922c965cc295ad
  - Book 1: 1858-1904
  - Book 2: 1904-1911
  - Book 3: 1911-1921
  - Book 4: 1922-1932
  - Book 5: 1933-1937
  - Book 6: 1938-1971
  - Book 7: 1972-ongoing
- Series 2: Coin collection card index, 1859-1904, bulk 1892-1901; 0.5 cubic feet (5 boxes)
  Open to all researchers.
  Saltus, J. Sanford, 1853-1922; Sage, Augustus B., 1842-1874; Card indexes; Parish, Daniel, 1842-1914
  Card index with detailed descriptions of various donated coins, sometimes including donor and date acquired, or indicating whether purchased along with price. Donors include Augustus B. Sage, Daniel Parish Jr., and J. Sanford Saltus.
- Series 3: Coin collection accession records by accession number, 1894, 1920-2004; 2.5 cubic feet (3 boxes)
  Users should also consult the following series in the Curatorial record group (RG2 [this record group]): Coin Collection Accession Records by Subject and Year.
  Users searching for cash and other donations should also consult the following series in the record group Development and Membership (RG3): (1) Donation Files and (2) Wills, Bequests, Gifts, and Special Funds Records.
  Estate records; Wills; Lists (Document genres); Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence; Chase Manhattan Bank Money Museum
  Contains a variety of coin collection accession records, such as acknowledgment letters, other correspondence, and unrestricted gift forms. Not all of the files contain the same types of records. Some contain materials such as wills, estate inventories, clippings, and coin lists. The “1980.66-1980.67 – Chase Manhattan Bank Money Museum” file has correspondence relating to an 1804 silver dollar, and includes the earliest materials in the series, an 1894 letter relating to the dollar.
    nnan0115/c_2d0dc5812a7e49a684cd4eb93583401e
  - Box 2 of 3
      nnan0115/c_11ad71754f6277030b8bc79914855019
    - 1992.2 to 1999.77
  - Box 3 of 3
      nnan0115/c_9863c52fabdeef08a5293abc47702a1b
    - 2000.1 to 2008.51
- Series 4: Coin collection accession records by subject and year, 1911-2007; 1 cubic foot (1 box)
  Users should also consult the following series in the Curatorial record group (RG2 [this record group]): Coin Collection Accession Records by Accession Number.
  Correspondence; Shipping records; Lists; Inventories
  Contains a variety of records including correspondence, shipping documents, coin lists and inventories, invoices, import and export licenses (1962-1968), and other materials relating to coins, medals, and other numismatic materials that were accessioned, offered, or otherwise considered of interest to the Society. In some cases the relevant accession number is written on the document. The series is a somewhat ad hoc gathering of materials relating to accessions that were filed in different ways over time, and includes stray files not easily placed elsewhere.
- Series 5: Coin collection deaccession records, 1958-2009; 1 cubic foot (1 box)
  Correspondence; Lists (Document genres); Auction catalogs
  Correspondence, auction catalogs, lists of coins to be auctioned, and disposition forms, all relating to the deaccessioning and disposition of duplicate and otherwise undesirable items in the collections.
- Series 6: Curatorial loan records, 1918-2007, bulk 1980-2007; 6 cubic feet (7 boxes and 1 loose item)
  Primarily organized into incoming (loans received) and outgoing (loans to other institutions). Portions of the records are arranged roughly chronologically or alphabetically, but overall the records appear to be unarranged.
  Agreements; Insurance records; Photographs; Correspondence; Agreements; Lists (Document genres); Exhibition records; Exhibition catalogs; Brochures
  Contains records pertaining to materials lent to ANS by other institutions (incoming loans), and items loaned out to other institutions by ANS (outgoing loans). Records on incoming loans include signed deposit agreements, certificates of insurance, lists of loaned items, photographs (occasionally), correspondence, and materials such as label texts relating to exhibits held at ANS. Records pertaining to outgoing loans include correspondence, facility reports from receiving institutions, certificates of insurance, printed materials such as brochures and exhibit catalogs from borrowing institutions, shipping documentation, loan request forms, photographs (occasionally), and lists of loaned items. Materials were most often loaned for exhibit, but in some cases were loaned for testing, as in the case of glass weights sent to be analyzed (but were not actually studied) at Corning Museum of Glass (1983, 1993) and items sent for microprobe analysis at the University of Illinois (1990). Also present are files on a theft of shipped ANS coins in an armed robbery at a post office in 1990; materials returned to the University of Pennsylvania (1939-2001); an album containing photographs of The Gwynne M. Andrews Collection loaned by the Metropolitan Museum of Art, February 16, 1931, along with images of coins loaned in 1930, 1935, 1936; the loan of the Bechtler coin press to The Mint Museum, Charlotte, North Carolina, from 1978 to 1991; a long-term loan from the New Jersey Historical Society of the Frederick Canfield numismatic collection, held at ANS from 1931 to 1994; and the buy-back of coins on long term loan to the ANS by the Metropolitan Museum of Art that were scheduled to be auctioned in 1973. The earliest materials are those pertaining to an ANS loan to the New-York Historical Society (1918).
    nnan0115/c_ad72938baaae35bf05d73f8fc354b038
  - Photograph Album
    Contains photographs of The Gwynne M. Andrews Collection loaned by the Metropolitan Museum of Art, February 16, 1931, and images of coins loaned in 1930, 1935, 1936.
- Series 7: Exhibition records, 1900-2010; 5.5 cubic feet (6 boxes and 1 loose item)
  Exposition universelle internationale de 1900 (Paris, France); Scudder, Janet, 1869-1940; Boyle, John J., 1851-1917; Fourcade, Dominique Philippe Jean; Correspondence; Photographs; Exhibition records; Exhibition catalogs; Exhibit scripts; Invitations; Brochures; Floor plans; Architectural drawings (Visual works); Logs (Records)
  For photographs from Exhibition of Early American Coinage (1942) see the Sydney Noe Papers in the ANS Archives.
  For additional materials relating to items loaned by and to the ANS for exhibits, see the Curatorial Loan Records series in this record group (RG2: Curatorial).
  Contains records relating to some of the exhibitions produced by the American Numismatic Society, most of which were held at the ANS headquarters building, though also included are files from the traveling exhibit program (1945-1970s) and a file on the Society’s exhibit at the Paris Exposition of 1900 that has correspondence, invoices, and insurance policy documents relating to the arrangements made for participating in the exhibition. The kinds and amounts of material available for each exhibit vary, with some represented by just an exhibition catalog or brochure and others having correspondence and photographs of pieces displayed. Several important early exhibits are represented, such as the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals (1910), from which is a large scrapbook containing photographs documenting the pieces loaned for the exhibit, mostly pasted in but with some loose, and others mounted on board, as in the case of several photographs from Dominique Philippe Jean Fourcade and Janet Scudder. (Two sets of photographs, showing the obverse and reverse of medals by John J. Boyle for The Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts and The Art Club of Philadelphia seem to have been misfiled in the scrapbook). Additionally, there is a register book used for the 1910 exhibit to log loaned items, a separate loan book, and loan delivery cards. There also is a set of proof sheets of coin photographs from an exhibit of U.S. colonial coins (1914). Records relating to an exhibit commemorating the bi-millennium of the birth of Caesar Augustus (1938) includes correspondence regarding loans and invitations as well as photographs of exhibited items. Materials from the Exhibition of Early American Coinage (1942) contains correspondence having to do with promoting the exhibit and regarding the items loaned for display. (For photographs from the exhibit, see the Sydney Noe Papers in the ANS Archives.) Files from the Exhibition of the Coinages of the Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern East (1948) contain exhibit label text and photographs. Two later exhibits are well documented: for The World of Coins (1983-2004), which occupied the Society’s Audubon headquarters West Hall during the two decades prior to its move downtown in 2004, there are plans, architectural drawings, outlines, scripts, and grant materials; for an exhibit celebrating the 100th anniversary of the New York Numismatic Club (2008) there are, among other things, loan forms with accompanying descriptions of the loaned items that were intended for use as exhibit text.
    nnan0115/c_2d4f0c3f4b96c55c1f6a2054d1beef26
  - Box 1 of 7
      nnan0115/c_dd49f40d4487afe18f89e49de918d4c1
    - Exhibitions – invitations and admission cards, early 20th c.?
    - Paris Exposition, 1900
    - Circular for the Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals, 1911
    - Augustan (Augustus) exhibition, 1938 (1 of 2)
    - Augustan (Augustus) exhibition, 1938 (2 of 2)
    - Augustan (Augustus) exhibition – Clippings, 1938
    - Augustan exhibition photograph book, 1938
    - Exhibition of Early American Coinage, 1942
    - Exhibition of Early American Coinage – Brochures, 1942
    - Exhibition of Early American Coinage – A-M, 1942
    - Exhibition of Early American Coinage – N-Z, 1942
    - Spanish exhibition – Hans M.F. Schulman, 1951
    - Traveling exhibition, 1945-1966
    - Traveling exhibits – Assembly instructions, undated
    - Traveling exhibit – Request, 1979
    - Traveling exhibit – George Washington in Medallic Art – Brochures, 1970s
    - Traveling exhibit – Coinage of Judaea – Brochures, undated
    - Traveling exhibit – Chinese Communist Money – Brochures, 1979
    - Coin exhibit photographs (Coins of the Centuries?) – 500 B.C. to 1 B.C., undated
    - Exhibition of the Coinages of the Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern East, 1948 (1 of 3)
    - Exhibition of the Coinages of the Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern East, 1948 (2 of 3)
    - Exhibition of the Coinages of the Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern East, 1948 (3 of 3)
    - Exhibit – Birds on Ancient Greek Coins – Photographs, 1972
    - Permanent exhibit photographic prints – Peace medals (?), John Paulding medal, Joan of Arc, circa 1950s-1980s
    - Exhibition? – Photographic prints of U.S. Mint buildings, 1980s?
    - Exhibit – An American in China, The L. Irvine Moffett Collection – Photographs, 1973
    - East and West Hall exhibit layout, 1953
    - Exhibition cases – Inventory and evaluation, 1964
    - Estimate of exhibition cases, 1964
    - Exhibits – Returned to vault, 1967
    - Harold Center exhibition space, 1983
    - Memoranda, correspondence, and photographs relating to exhibits and other issues, 1970-1986
    - Exhibit – Presidential campaign buttons, 1960s?
    - Exhibit – The Flight of Man, 1973
    - Exhibits – Charles Edison Fund, 1976
    - Exhibits – Brochures, undated
  - Box 2 of 7
      nnan0115/c_8b6b4f0410fa207df83d2fe3e86336cd
    - FIDEM
    - American Medallic Sculpture Association exhibit catalogs, 1983-1984
    - Beaux arts medal - Book and exhibit, 1988
    - Exhibit - The Beaux-Arts Medal in America - Brochures, 1987-1988
    - The Beaux-Arts Medal in America
    - Exhibit - Indian Peace Medals - Brochure
    - Exhibit catalog – The Currency of Fame: Portrait Medals of the Renaissance, 1994 (two loose copies)
    - Exhibit catalog – Treasures of Ancient Coinage, 1996
    - Exhibit catalog – The Proud Republic: Dutch Medals of the Golden Age, 1997 (three loose copies)
    - Exhibit catalog – New Ideas in Medallic Sculpture – Saltus, 1998-1999
    - Exhibit – Drachmas, Dubloons, and Dollars – Brochures, circa 2001
    - Docent meeting materials – Federal Reserve, 2001
    - Exhibit script – Drachmas Doubloons, and Dollars – The History of Money, circa 2001
    - Byzantine Hoard – Israel Antiquities Authority – 2003
    - Byzantine Hoard, 2003
    - Exhibit – Full Circle: The Olympic Heritage in Coins and Medals – Brochure, 2003-2004
    - Olympics, 2003
    - Olympic exhibit, 2005 (1 of 4)
    - Olympic exhibit, 2005 (2 of 4)
    - Olympic exhibit, 2005 (3 of 4)
    - Olympic exhibit, 2005 (4 of 4)
    - Olympic – Bernth Ahlstrom, 2006
    - New York Steel exhibition, 2005 (1 of 2)
    - New York Steel exhibition, 2005 (2 of 2)
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Friends of, 2005
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Image requests, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Panels, cases, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Loeb & Barrera, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Announcement, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – List and labels, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition prep, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition catalog – Grant application, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Grant, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Insurance, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens newsletter, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Brochures, magazine and newspaper articles, and DVD of film, 2007
    - Exhibit catalog – One Hundred Years of Solicitude: Collecting by the New York Numismatic Club, 2008 (two loose copies)
  - Box 3 of 7 - World of Coins exhibit
      nnan0115/c_f559d6741941d2e88f34d9ea8a5819b2
    - Exhibit – World of Coins – Brochure, undated
    - New York State Council on the Arts (NYSCA) – World of Money, 1979
    - World of Coins, 1978-1979
    - Grants – Including exhibit, 1977
    - World of Coins – Grants and other preliminary, 1977
    - World of Coins – Prototype, 1978
    - World of Coins exhibition information, 1983-1996
    - World of Coins – Draft, undated
    - Exhibit text – Master copy
    - World of Coins exhibit outline, 1978 (1 of 2)
    - World of Coins exhibit outline, 1978 (2 of 2)
    - Secondary panels, undated
    - Polo
    - Before
    - Renaissance
    - Machinery
    - Dollar
    - Modern Economy
    - Money/Message
    - Denarius
    - Solidus/Byzantine
    - World of Coins - Architectural drawings of floor and exhibit plans
      nnan0115/c_f1f5d8f2f47e96203e89ccdb271120d5
    - NYNC item list
    - NYNC exhibit – Insurance
    - NYNC exhibit – Labels/Description
    - NYNC catalog
    - NYNC exhibit
    - NYNC centennial exhibit write ups
    - NYNC exhibit forms
    - NYNC exhibit layout
    - NYNC history/medals panel
    - Alexander, David – Loan forms
    - Cuhaj, George – Loan forms
    - Erlichman, Jay – Loan forms
    - Fleishmann, David – Loan forms
    - Galst, Jay – Loan forms
    - Haggerty, Jerry – Loan forms
    - Herzon, John – Loan forms
    - Hoge, Bob – Loan forms
    - Kagen, Jonathan – Loan forms
    - Knapp, Bob – Loan forms
    - Lande, David – Loan forms
    - Low, Darrell – Loan forms
    - Margolis, Richard – Loan forms
    - Marinescu, Constantin – Loan forms
    - Menchell, David – Loan forms
    - Miller, Scott – Loan forms
    - Parris, Michael – Loan forms
    - Rezak, Ira – Loan forms
    - Sacks, Bob – Loan forms
    - Schaaf, Robert – Loan forms
    - Scher, Steve – Loan forms
    - Siboni, Roger – Loan forms
    - Simpson, David – Loan forms
    - Terranova, Tony – Loan forms
    - Tesorlero, Tom – Loan forms
    - Tomasko, Mark – Loan forms
    - Van Alfen, Peter – Loan forms
    - Witschonke, Rick – Loan forms
  - Box 5 of 7 - Flat file and oversized
      nnan0115/c_e974712d4a001b5419d8a926216b9dfc
    - Spiral bound outline of the World of Coins exhibit (6 loose copies)
    - World of coins architectural drawings of exhibits and floor plans (loose)
    - Exhibit – U.S. colonial coins – Photographs, proof sheets for illustrations, 1914
    - Augustan exhibit – Photostats, 1938
    - World of Coins visitors log book, 1990-1995
    - Exhibit labels – Washington exhibit, undated
    - International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals loan book, 1910
    - International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals loan cards, 1910
  - Box 6 of 7 - International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals photograph album, 1910
  - 7 of 7 [loose] - International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals register log book, 1910
- Series 8: Envelopes from Bates and Heaton coin collections, 1984-1985; 1.5 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Envelopes; Bates, George Eugene; Heaton, Charles T
  Empty annotated coin envelopes from the George Eugene Bates Byzantine coin collection (1984.61) and the Charles T. Heaton coin club medals collection (1985.67)
    nnan0115/c_193a8a40e7182a5b7bb408439c803b73
  - Box 1 of 2: Bates
  - Box 2 of 2: Heaton
- Series 9: Howland Wood curator correspondence and other material, 1913-1937; 10 cubic feet (12 boxes)
  Mostly official correspondence from Howland Wood’s work as curator of the American Numismatic Society (ANS). Many of the letters are to and from dealers, ANS members, and the general public and involve matters such as the authentication and value of individual coins as well as coin donations, purchasing, items sent on approval, and other efforts to add to and document the ANS collections, including its holdings in Indian Peace Medals and medals relating to World War I. Occasionally, coin rubbings and photographs are included. Also discussed are building security issues, such as a theft of coins from the J.P. Morgan and D.O. Mills collections (Newell, 1927); employee matters, such as hiring an assistant curator upon the death of Robert Robertson in 1937 (e.g., Duffield, Jan. 27, 1937), and lists of employees and salaries (see Union Trust Company). Other topics include Wood’s work as editor of the American Journal of Numismatics, such as discussions of article content and production issues; photographing and casting of coins; cleaning of coins (e.g., Hopkins, March 4, 1931 and Oliveira, May 16, 1933); exhibits; the return of the Andrew Zabriskie collection, with a catalog of Polish coins returned (1924); the addition to the building at Audubon Terrace (see Eidlitz, 1921-1934); the Bechtler coin press donated to the ANS (Tapp, 1926-1928); the loan of the Frederick A. Canfield collection by the New Jersey Historical Society (1930-1931); psychologist and collector Edward B. Titchener of Cornell University; and the Henry A. Ramsden Far Eastern collection, including a note to John Robinson about the terms of Ramsden’s will, a numbered list of Ramsden coins, and related materials, such as those pertaining to Far Eastern collector Giuseppe Ros, Italian consulate general in Shangai (R, 1913-1921). In addition to the correspondence are research materials, including notebooks on Indian Bull and Horseman series; files on Bryan Money, Mexican coins, Ethiopian (Abyssinian) coins, American medals (1918-1921), and Indian Peace Medals (1917); a handwritten index to the Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland (1837-1911), The Indian Antiquary (1877-1919), and the Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal (1832-1910); and typed curator and committee reports (1913-1927).
  Howland Wood (1877-1938) was born in New Bedford, Massachusetts, and graduated from Brown University in 1900. He became a member of the ANS in 1909. By 1913 he had been appointed Curator, remaining in this position until his death in 1938. At that time, the Society only maintained a single curator, with two assistants. Despite the limited size of the staff, during Wood's tenure the Society's collections increased significantly, from 50,000 to almost 200,000 specimens. In addition to his curatorial duties, Wood also served as editor of the American Journal of Numismatics from 1910 to 1920. In 1920, Wood became only the third recipient of the Society's Archer M. Huntington Medal Award. Outside of the ANS, Wood also served as secretary to the American Numismatic Association from 1905 to 1909 and then as governor and chairman of the ANA's board from 1909 to 1912. After Wood's death, Edward T. Newell (ANS President, 1916-1941) eulogized Wood as "the ideal Curator," noting that "Howland Wood was one of those rare geniuses who combined an inherited urge to collect, an insatiable curiosity as to the 'why' and the 'wherefore,' and an orderly mind which could not brook obvious gaps or disorderly arrangement."
  See also Howland Wood personal correspondence, 1873, 1902-1938.
  Wood, Howland, 1877-1938; Zabriskie, Andrew C. (Andrew Christian), 1853-1916; Morgan, J. P. (John Pierpont), 1867-1943; Robertson, Robert, 1869-1937; Robinson, John, 1846-1925; Ros, Giuseppe; Ramsden, Henry A., d. 1915; Titchener, Edward Bradford, 1867-1927; Canfield, Frederick A. (Frederick Alexander), 1849-1926; New Jersey Historical Society; American Journal of Numismatics; American Numismatic Society; D.O. Mills & Co. (Sacramento, Calif.); Rubbings (Visual works); Correspondence; Photographs; Notebooks; Reports; Indexes (Reference sources)
    nnan0115/c_f0d6ea9289deefd32117893bb58bc540
  - Box 1 of 12
      nnan0115/c_82e2963ef467461993c9ed13094e54bd
    - A-Z (Zerbe), 1913-1919
    - A, 1918-1919
    - A, 1918-1919
    - Ae-Am, 1924-1929
    - An-Az, 1924-1929